# **CURRICULUM VITAE**

# Michael L. Treglia, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Research Associate Department of Biological Science – OH 304 University of Tulsa 800 S. Tucker Dr., Tulsa, OK 74105

Phone: +1-918-631-3465

E-mail: mike-treglia@utulsa.edu
Website: <a href="http://mltconsecol.github.io/">http://mltconsecol.github.io/</a>

### **Research Interests**

My research is focused on identifying conservation strategies for endangered species while advancing analytical techniques and our understanding of ecology. I integrate methods from statistics, GIS, and remote sensing to study landscape-scale patterns and processes, often learning new skills and working with collaborators. My research has largely focused on herpetofauna, though I am interested in extending my work to other taxa and entire ecosystems.

#### **Education**

2009-2014.	Ph.D., Dept. of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
2007-2010	M.S., Dept. of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
2004-2007	B.S., Natural Resources, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY.

Research Experience		
2014-Pres	<b>Postdoctoral Research Associate.</b> Focused on understanding relationships between environmental variability across multiple scales and biodiversity; working as part of the Oklahoma NSF-EPSCoR Program. Supervisor: Dr. Ron Bonett, University of Tulsa.	
2009-14	<b>Dissertation.</b> Title: <i>Conservation of the endangered Arroyo Toad across multiple scales.</i> Five chapters focused on identifying threats to, and conservation opportunities for, the Arroyo Toad ( <i>Anaxyrus californicus</i> ). Supervisor: Dr. Lee Fitzgerald, Texas A&M University.	
2007-10	<b>Master's Thesis.</b> Title: A translocated population of the St. Croix Ground Lizard: Analyzing its detection probability and investigating its impacts on the local prey base. Four chapters focused on understanding the ecology of the endangered St. Croix Ground Lizard (Ameiva polops), and examining effects of the species' detectability on monitoring. Supervisor: Dr. Lee Fitzgerald, Texas A&M University.	
2007	<b>Research Assistant.</b> Collected field data for a long-term study on relationships between forestry management, coarse woody debris, and biodiversity. Supervisor: Dr. Stephen Morreale, Cornell University.	
2005-07	<b>Research Assistant.</b> Maintained collection of live reptiles for research and teaching, including over 40 venomous snakes and lizards. Supervisor: Dr. Harry Greene, Cornell University.	
2006	<b>NSF-REU Intern.</b> Conducted undergraduate research on reptiles and amphibians of St. Vincent, Lesser Antilles, resulting in four publications. Supervisor: Dr. Robert Powell, Avila University.	

2004-05 **Lab Assistant.** Set up soil samples for chemical analysis with gas chromatograph. Supervisor: Dr. Joseph Yavitt, Cornell University.

- 2003-04 **Intern**. Bred poison dart frogs and analyzed effects of different diets on growth and development rates of the tadpoles. This research was submitted to Intel Science Talent Search Competition. Supervisor: Ms. Cathy Eser, Staten Island Zoo.
- 2002-04 **Intern.** Collected field data on pond turtles in New York for long-term research projects. Supervisor: Mr. David Karrmann, American Museum of Natural History.

## Fellowships, Grants, and Awards

- 2013-14 Tom Slick Doctoral Dissertation Fellowship. College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Texas A&M University. \$25,000.
- Willie May Harris Fellowship for Outstanding Teaching Assistants, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Texas A&M University. \$12,000.
   E. E. Williams Research Grant, The Herpetologists' League. \$1,000.

Sylvia Scholarship, Mensa Foundation. \$600.

- 2012, 2013 Travel Grants, Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Program at Texas A&M. \$675; \$700.
- 2010-12 NSF-IGERT Traineeship for the Applied Biodiversity Science Doctoral Program at Texas A&M University. \$84,000.
- Outstanding Master's Student, Department of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&M University.
- 2008 2<sup>nd</sup> Place for Talk, "An Invasive Anole, *Anolis sagrei*, on St. Vincent and its Potential Impact on Native Anoles." Student Research Week, Texas A&M University.
- 2007-08 Regents Graduate Fellowship, Texas A&M University. \$15,000.
- 2007 Ullman Scholarship, Cornell University. \$500.
- 2005 Arthur H. and Karin A. Nelson Scholarship, Cornell University. \$500.

### **Publications** (In Prep. Manuscripts are available upon request)

- Fitzgerald, L.A., **M.L. Tregli**a, N. Angeli, T.J. Hibbitts, D.J. Leavitt, A.L. Subalusky, I. Lundgren, and Z. Hillis-Starr. 2015. Determinants of successful establishment of a new population of the critically endangered St. Croix Ground Lizard (Teiidae: *Ameiva polops*). *Restoration Ecology*. DOI: 10.1111/rec.12248
  - **Treglia, M.L.**, R.N. Fisher, and L.A. Fitzgerald. 2015 Integrating potential and current species distribution models to identify conservation opportunities for an endangered toad. *PLoS ONE*. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0131628
  - Wang, H.H., C.L. Wonka, **M.L. Treglia**, W.E. Grant, F.E. Smeins, W.E. Rogers. 2015. Species distribution modeling of an endangered endemic orchid, *Spiranthes parksii* (Correll). *AoB Plants*. DOI: 10.1093/aobpla/plv039
- Treglia, M.L., J. Valiulis, D. J. Leavitt, and L.A. Fitzgerald. 2013. Establishment of the Puerto Rican Ground Lizard (*Ameiva exsul*: Teiidae), on St. Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands: a threat to native fauna. *Caribbean Journal of Science* 47(2-3): 373-378.
- Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. 2011. Translocation of the St. Croix ground lizard to Buck Island Reef National Monument, St. Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands. Pp. 109-115. In. Soorae P.S. (ed.) (2011). Global Re-introduction Perspectives: 2011. More case studies from around the globe. Gland, Switzerland: IUCN/SSC Re-introduction Specialist Group and Abu Dhabi, UAE: Environment Agency-Abu Dhabi. Xiv +250 pp.
- **Treglia, M.L.,** O. Ramirez. 2009. *Nerodia rhombifer*. Geographic distribution. *Herpetological Review* 40(2):238.

- Treglia, M.L., A.J. Muensch, R. Powell, and J.S. Parmerlee, Jr. 2008. An invasive anole, *Anolis sagrei* on St. Vincent and its potential impact on native anoles. *Caribbean Journal of Science* 44(2):251–256.
  - Henderson, R.W., **M.L. Treglia**, and S.D. Powell. 2008. *Corallus cookii*. Foraging. *Herpetological Review* 38(4):466.
- Powell, S.D., **M.L. Treglia**, R.W. Henderson, and R. Powell. 2007. Treeboas in the West Indies: responses of *Corallus cookii* and *C. grenadensis* to disturbed habitats. Pp. 374–387 in: R. W. Henderson and R. Powell (eds.). *Biology of the Boas and Pythons*. Eagle Mountain Publ., Utah.
- In Prep. **Treglia, M.L.**, S.D. Martin, A.L. Boardman, R.M. Bonett. Does habitat stability promote the loss of a complex life cycle stage in a stream-associated salamanders. Target Journal: *Functional Ecology*.
  - **Treglia, M.L.**, A.C. Landon, G.T. Kyle, R.N. Fisher, L.A. Fitzgerald. Multi-scale effects of land cover conditions on a riparian habitat specialist. Target Journal: *Conservation Biology.*
  - **Treglia, M.L.** and L.A. Fitzgerald. A field experiment on the effects of an active-foraging lizard on its invertebrate prey base. Target Journal: *Journal of Zoology*.

#### **Technical Reports and Other Documents**

- Treglia, M.L. 2015. An Introduction to GIS Using QGIS (v. 2.6.1). Training material for QGIS, available at: <a href="http://mltconsecol.github.io/QGIS-Tutorial/">http://mltconsecol.github.io/QGIS-Tutorial/</a>.
- Treglia, M.L. 2014. Results of surveys for the endangered Arroyo Toad (*Anaxyrus californicus*) in 2013. Annual Report to the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and California Department of Fish and Wildlife.
- Treglia, M. L. and L. A. Fitzgerald. 2010 The translocation of the St. Croix ground lizard, Ameiva polops, to Buck Island Reef National Monument. Final Report to the National Park Service, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and Virgin Islands Department of Planning and Natural Resources.
  - **Treglia, M. L.** and L. A. Fitzgerald. 2010 Population estimation of the St. Croix ground lizard, *Ameiva polops*, on Protestant Cay and Ruth Cay, St. Croix, United States Virgin Islands. Final Report to the United States Fish and Wildlife Service (Cooperative Agreement 401917J125).
- **Treglia, M.L.** 2006. An annotated checklist of the amphibians and reptiles of St. Vincent, West Indies. *Iguana* 13: 252–263.

#### **Oral Presentations** (\* indicates Invited Presentation)

- \*Treglia, M.L. Landscape-Scale Approaches Guide Conservation and Inform Ecology in a Complex World. *Lecture to the Anthropology Department at the University of Tulsa*.
  - **Treglia, M.L.**, S.D. Martin, A.L. Boardman, and R.M. Bonett. Multi-scale influences of environmental variability on life history strategies of the Oklahoma salamander. *World Congress of the International Association of Landscape Ecologists, Portland, OR.*
- Wang, H.-H., C.L. Wonkka, **M.L. Treglia**, W.E. Grant, F.E. Smeins, and W.E. Rogers. Determinants and likelihood of occurrence of an endangered endemic orchid (*Spiranthes parksii* (Correll)) in central Texas. *Texas Plant Conservation Conference*, *Austin*, *TX*.
  - \*Treglia, M.L. Multi-Scale Conservation in an Altered Landscape: The Case of the Endangered Arroyo Toad in Southern California. *Department of Biological Science, The University of Tulsa, Tulsa, OK.*

- **Treglia, M.L.** and G.T. Kyle. Estimating effects of land cover at multiple scales on habitat for the endangered arroyo toad. In J. Franklin, J.M. Sierra-Diaz, and L. Sweet (Chairs), *Impacts of Global Change: Linking Across Scales*. Symposium presented at the *Annual Meeting of the U.S. Regional Association of the International Association for Landscape Ecology, Anchorage, AK*.
- Treglia, M.L. and R.N. Fisher. Integrating Historic and Current Distribution Models of an Endangered Species to Benefit Conservation. *Annual Meeting of the U.S. Regional Association of the International Association for Landscape Ecology, Austin, TX.* 
  - \*Treglia, M.L. Conservation of the Endangered St. Croix Ground Lizard. *Lecture to Aggies for the Protection of Endangered Species at Texas A&M University.*
- \*Treglia, M.L. Manifold GIS: Exploring the Capabilities of an Alternative GIS Package. *U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center San Diego Field Station. San Diego, CA.*Treglia, M.L. Anthropogenic Disturbances and Conservation of Endangered Amphibians in a Semi-arid Landscape: A Proposal Talk. *12<sup>th</sup> Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.*
- Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. Effects of an Insular Lizard Translocation on the Local Invertebrate Assemblage. *Annual Meeting of the Ecological Society of America, Pittsburgh, PA.*Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. Impacts of a Translocated Lizard on an Island Arthropod Assemblage. *11th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.*
- Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. Effects of Detectability on Lizard Population Estimates.

  Annual Meeting of the Southwestern Association of Naturalists, Monterrey, Nuevo Leon, MX.
- Treglia, M.L. The Translocation of an Extirpated Lizard in the Caribbean: A Proposal Talk. Student Research Week/9th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

  Treglia, M.L., A.J. Muensch, R. Powell, J.S. Parmerlee, Jr. An Invasive Anole: Anolis sagrei on St. Vincent and its Potential Impact on Native Anoles. Student Research Week/9th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

#### **Poster Presentations**

- Treglia, M.L. and M.E. Young. Utilizing Patch Metrics to Improve Classification of Remote Sensing Imagery. World Congress of the International Association of Landscape Ecologists, Portland, OR.
- 2014 Lovette, J. T. Chang, **M.L. Treglia**, T. Gan, J. Duncan. Assessing Ecohydrological Impacts of Forest Disturbance Using Open Source Software. *Annual Meeting of the American Geophysical Union, San Francisco, CA*.
- Treglia, M.L. and A.C. Landon. Integrative Research for Biodiversity Conservation and Water Resource Management. Student Conference on Conservation Science New York. New York, NY.
   Treglia, M.L. and R.N. Fisher. Presence-Only Modeling to Understand the Historic Distribution of an Endangered Toad. 7th World Congress of Herpetology. Vancouver, BC, Canada
- Treglia, M.L. Conserving an Endangered Toad in a Dynamic Landscape. 1st Annual NSF-IGERT Online Competition. Available online at: <a href="http://www.igert.org/posters2011/posters/94">http://www.igert.org/posters2011/posters/94</a>
- Treglia, M.L. Effects of Detectability on Population Estimates of the Ground-Dwelling Lizard, Ameiva polops. 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

# **Teaching Experience**

2015 Instructor for *Graduate Seminar on Spatial Ecology*, University of Tulsa, Tulsa, OK Instructor for *Landscape Analysis and Modeling*, University of Tulsa, Tulsa, OK. 2014 Half-day course on QGIS, as part of the Open Source for Open Science Workshop for the Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Program, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX. TA for *Herpetology*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX. 2010, 2013 2012 Guest Lecturer for class, Recreation Management of Wildlands, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX. 2007, 2012 TA for *Natural History of the Vertebrates*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX. TA for Fundamentals of Ecology Lab, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX. 2009 2008 TA for *Natural History of the Invertebrates*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.

### **Service**

2014-15	Reviewer for E.E. Williams Research Grant Program, The Herpetologists' League.
2011-12	Co-Chair of the 13th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.
2010-11	Treasurer of the Association of Graduate Wildlife and Fisheries Scientists.
2009-10	President of the Association of Graduate Wildlife and Fisheries Scientists.
	Web-Designer for the 11th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.
	Judge for Student Research Week, Texas A&M University.
2007-08	Mentor for Undergraduate Research Group at Texas A&M University, supervised by Dr. Lee Fitzgerald.
2006-07	President of the Cornell Herpetological Society.
2005-06	Treasurer of the Cornell Herpetological Society.
2004-06	Docent at Staten Island Zoo.

**Reviewer for the following journals:** Ecological Modeling; Herpetologica; Herpetological Conservation and Biology; Journal of Applied Ecology; Herpetological Review; Biological Invasions; Journal of Biogeography; Applied Herpetology; African Journal of Herpetology.

**Member of the following organizations:** Society for the Study of Amphibians and Reptiles; U.S. Regional Association of the International Association for Landscape Ecology.

**Active member of the following software listserves:** QGIS-User List (Quantum [Q]GIS); R-Sig-Geo (R Spatial Analysis).

**Contributor to the following R Packages:** pgirmess (available on CRAN); Rfrag (available at the Fragstats Website)

#### **Technical Skills**

- Programming in R
- Multivariate Statistics and Machine Learning Methods
- GIS, Remote Sensing, and LiDAR Processing with Free and Open Source Software, ArcGIS and Google Earth Engine
- Git Version Control System
- Familiarity with Python, Bash, SQL, LaTeX, and Stata